Guide to the Records of the Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean RISM RG 10
New York University Archives
Records of the Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean
Bulk, 1960-1963
1959-1971
RISM RG 10
New York University Archives
1.0 linear feet
On January 14, 1960, the Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean was conducted by the Caribbean Federation for Mental Health (CFMH) under the supervision of the World Federation for Mental Health and the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM). The first of its kind in the Caribbean, the comparative study explored local and regional patterns of mental illness and health through a number of influential factors, including migration, occupation, education, marital status, and family history. Source: Records of Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean, Series I, Folder 5 Records of Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean, Series IV, Folder 1
Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM).
Box 1-2
Related Archival Materials
Related Material
Records of the RISM Medical School Attitude Questionnaire (MSAQ)
Records of the RISM Bolivia Project
Records of the Puerto Rico Study
RISM Vertical Files
Records of the Interuniversity Consortium
Separated Materials
Statistical records associated with the research were analyzed by the Puerto Rican government and were retained by their National Archives.
Provenance
The Caribbean Mental Health Census was created by the Caribbean Federation for Mental Health (CFMH) under the supervision of the World Federation for Mental Health and the Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM).
Access Restrictions
Some of the materials in this collection may be restricted. Please contact the University Archives for details.
Additionally, please note that this collection is stored
offsite
, and you must contact the repository to schedule access.
Arrangement
The Records of the Census of Mental Hospitals have been organized in chronological order according to the following series:
Series I: Census Reports and Research Programs
Series II: Field Manuals and Questionnaires
Series III: Correspondence
Series IV: Conference Papers
Historical Note
The Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean was a comprehensive, one-day research project organized by the Caribbean Federation for Mental Health (CFMH). Founded at the Second Caribbean Conference for Mental Health in April 1959, the CFMH conducted the project on January 14, 1960, under the supervision of the World Federation for Mental Health and the Research Institute for the Study of Man.
The census research project was the first systematic effort in the region to collect cross-cultural epidemiological data on the socio-psychiatric characteristics of mental patients. Census research of this popuation also provided a comparative look at the local and regional patterns of mental illness.
Enumerators and hospital staff were provided with field instruction manuals and questionnaires in English, Dutch, Spanish, and French. Approximately 9,000 patients in mental hospitals in Antigua, the Bahamas, Barbados, Guyana, Haiti, Jamaica, Martinique, Puerto Rico, Trinidad, and the U.S. Virgin Islands participated in the study.
The research findings, analyzed with the assistance of the Bureau of Registry and Statistics of Puerto Rico, provided information on a broad spectrum of variables in mental illness, including such contributing factors as migration, occupation, education, marital status, and family history. The final report concluded that standardization was needed in treatment procedures, diagnostic criteria, and nomenclature. Recommendations for institutional recordkeeping procedures, the development of in-training programs for mental health personnel, the exchange of information on administrative and technical problems, research on therapeutic measures, and release rates on familial and social factors in mental illness were also included in the report.
Source: Records of Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean, Series I, Folder 5 Records of Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean, Series IV, Folder 1
Scope and Contents
The records of the Census of the Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean consists of 1.0 linear foot (2 AB) and spans the years 1960 to 1971 (plus undated material), with the bulk of the materials generated between 1960 and 1963.
The collection, which includes census reports, research programs, field manuals, questionnaires, correspondence, and conference papers, has been arranged in four series and organized chronologically within each series. The four series are as follows:
Series I: Census Reports and Research Programs (1960-1963)
Series II: Field Manuals and Questionnaires (1961), which includes questionnaires in English, Dutch, and French
Series III: Correspondence (1962-1971), including correspondence regarding board meetings, social work education, and requests for census reports; and
Series IV: Conference Papers (1961-1971; undated).
Research Institute for the Study of Man (RISM).; Rubin, Vera D.; Aruba; Bahamas.; Barbados.; Caribbean Federation for Mental Health.; Curacao (Netherlands Antilles); Guadeloupe.; Guyana.; Haiti.; Jamaica.; Martinique.; Mental health |z Caribbean Area.; Mental health.; Psychiatric hospitals.; Puerto Rico.; Trinidad and Tobago.; Virgin Islands.; West Indies.
- Series I: Census Reports and Research Programs, 1960-1963
  - Report on a Meeting Held on 27th to 31st October at UCWI to Discuss the Establishment of a Census Research Programme Based on the 1960 Population Census-original (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Research Programme Based on 1960 Census of West Indes- original (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Research Programme Based on 1960 Census of the West Indes- fascimile (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Draft Report [incomplete], final on the Census of Caribbean Mental Hospitals, 1961 August (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report on the Census of Caribbean Mental Hospitals [Draft], 1961 August (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report on the Meeting of the Advisory Committee on the Census Research Programme, held at UCWI, 1961 September (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of the N.Y. Association for the Caribbean Federation for Mental Health; CFMH Newsletter No. 1, 1962 February-March (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Report on a Meeting Held on 27th to 31st October at UCWI to Discuss the Establishment of a Census Research Programme Based on the 1960 Population Census- facsimile (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous research papers, clippings, notes, 1962 March, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Caribbean Project Report and Recommendations, Clara A. Kaiser, Unitarian Service Committee, Inc., Boston, Mass., 1963 March (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Field Manuals and Questionnaires, 1961
  - Mental Hospital Census Field Manual [complete], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mental Hospital Census Field Manual, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Questionnaires- English, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Questionnaires- Dutch, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Questionnaires- French, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1962-1971
  - Correspondence, 1962 March-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963 January-February (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1965 September (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1966 August-September (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1966 October-November (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1967 February-March (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1967 April-May (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1970 May-December (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1971 March (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Conference Papers
  - Report on the Census of Mental Hospitals in the Caribbean: Working Paper for the 3rd Conference of the Caribbean Federation for Mental Health, Kingston, Jamaica, 1961 April (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mental Health in International Perspective, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Services for Mental Illness and Mental Health, Conference Details, 1961 September (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fourth Caribbean Conference for Mental Health: Report of Group A Training Facilities in the Mental Health Field, 1963 April (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fourth Caribbean Conference for Mental Health: Mental Health Trainee Stipends in Social Work 1962-1963, 1963 April (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fourth Caribbean Conference for Mental Health: "Group Therapy among Alcoholics at the St. Ann's Hospital, Trinidad," Miss Heather Pinto, 1963 April (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, "Remarks on Community Health," by Marvin E. Perkins, M.D., 1963 April-May (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Leadership and Survival" by Mottram Torre at the Third Annual Conference of the Congress of Scientists on Survival, 1964 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Program brochure, application for the Seventh Biennial Conference for Mental Health, 1969 July-August (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bulletin, published by the World Federation for Mental Health, notes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Research Potentials in the Lesser Antilles," by Leo A. Estel [conference unknown], undated (Box 2, Folder 20)